Nguyen Quang Hieu

Email: hieu.nguyen-1@student.uts.edu.au
 Skype: hieu1204@gmail.com
 Personal website: [Link]
 Google Scholar: [Link]

BRIEF BIO

I am currently a PhD candidate at the University of Technology Sydney (UTS) in Australia. I focus on applied machine learning techniques for wireless communications and networking. I have special interests in deep reinforcement learning, generative models, probabilistic graphical models, and their potential applications in communications and networking systems. My contributions to the research fields include blockchain networks, integrated sensing-communications, edge computing, virtual reality, brain-computer interfaces, and 3D body tracking, but please see [Scholar] for a more complete list. Before joining UTS, I worked as a research assistant at Nanyang Technological University, Singapore, from 2019 to 2021. Before that, I obtained a Bachelor's degree from Hanoi University of Science and Technology, Vietnam, in 2018.

EDUCATION

University of Technology Sydney, New South Wales, Australia

• Ph.D candidate in Electrical and Data Engineering

Nov 2021 - now

- Supervisor: Dr. Hoang Dinh
- Focus: Wireless Communications, Reinforcement Learning, Deep Learning, Optimization

Hanoi University of Science and Technology (HUST), Hanoi, Vietnam

Bachelor in Electronics and Telecommunications Engineering

Aug 2013 – Jun 2018

- Cumulative GPA: 3.01/4 (7.72/10)
- Thesis (score): Integrating Trickle timing in Software-Defined WSNs for energy efficiency (9.8/10)
- Supervisor: Assoc. Prof. Nguyen Huu Thanh
- Focus: Wireless Sensor Networks, Energy-efficient routing/scheduling, Software Defined Networking

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Computer Networks and Communications Lab (CNCL), School of Computer Science and Engineering, Nanyang Technological University

Research Engineer

Apr 2019 – Oct 2021

- Supervisor: Prof. Dusit Niyato
- Focus: Resource allocation in wireless networks, Deep reinforcement learning, Blockchain.
- Activities:
 - Develop a deep reinforcement learning-based algorithm to optimize energy, latency, and CPU resources in blockchain-based/distributed machine learning networks.
 - Develop energy forecasting models for solar panels system using deep learning.

Future Internet Laboratory, School of Electronics and Telecommunications, HUST

Undergraduate Research Student

Aug 2016 – Mar 2019

- Supervisors: Assoc. Prof. Nguyen Huu Thanh
- Focus: Internet of Things, SDN/NFV, Network Security
- Activities
 - Develop a routing mechanism and design a software controller in Wireless Sensor Networks based on Software Defined Networking for energy-efficient routing.
 - Optimize data scheduling in Wireless Sensor Networks based on Time Slotted Channel Hopping (TSCH) for energy
 efficiency and data reliability. Proposed algorithm is implemented in a real-world testbed which consists of 70 sensors.

PUBLICATIONS

JOURNALS

- [J8] N. Q. Hieu, D. N. Nguyen, D. T. Hoang, and E. Dutkiewicz, "When virtual reality meets rate splitting multiple access: A joint communication and computation approach," *IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications*, vol. 41, no. 5, pp. 1536-1548, May 2023 (IF=16.4, Q1).
- [J7] N. Q. Hieu, D. T. Hoang, D. Niyato, D. N. Nguyen, D. I. Kim, and A. Jamalipour, "Joint power allocation and rate control for rate splitting multiple access networks with covert communications," *IEEE Transactions on Communications*, vol. 71, no. 4, pp. 2274-2287, Apr. 2023 (IF=8.3, Q1).
- [J6] N. Q. Hieu, D. T. Hoang, D. Niyato, P. Wang, D. In Kim, and C. Yuen, "Transferable deep reinforcement learning framework for autonomous vehicles with joint radar-data communications," *IEEE Transactions on Communications*, vol. 7, no. 8, Aug. 2022 (IF=8.3, Q1).
- [J5] N. Q. Hieu, T. T. Anh, N. C. Luong, D. Niyato, D. I. Kim, and E. Elmroth, "Resource management for blockchain-enabled federated learning: A deep reinforcement learning approach," *IEEE Networking Letters*, vol. 4, no. 3, Sep. 2022.

- [J4] K. S. H. Ong, W. Wang, N. Q. Hieu, D. Niyato, and T. Friedrichs, "Predictive maintenance model for IIoT-based manufacturing: A transferable deep reinforcement learning approach", *IEEE Internet of Things Journal*, vol. 9, no. 17, Sep. 2022 (IF=10.6, Q1).
- [J3] N. Q. Hieu, D. T. Hoang, N. C. Luong, and D. Niyato, "Optimal power allocation for rate splitting communications with deep reinforcement learning", *IEEE Wireless Communications Letters*, vol. 10, no. 12, Oct 2021 (IF=6.3, Q1).
- [J2] N. V. Tam, N. Q. Hieu, N. T. T. Van, N. C. Luong, D. Niyato, and D. I. Kim, "Adaptive task offloading in coded edge computing: A deep reinforcement learning approach", *IEEE Communications Letters*, vol. 25, no. 12, Sep 2021 (IF=4.1, Q1).
- [J1] N. Q. Hieu, D. T. Hoang, N. C. Luong, and D. Niyato, "iRDRC: A real-time intelligent dual-functional radar-communication system for automotive vehicles", *IEEE Wireless Communications Letters*, vol. 9, no. 12, Aug 2020 (IF=6.3, Q1).

CONFERENCES

- [C5] N. Q. Hieu, D. T. Hoang, D. N. Nguyen, and E. Dutkiewicz, "Toward BCI-enabled Metaverse: A Joint Learning and Resource Allocation Approach," *IEEE Global Communications Conference*, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, December 2023, accepted.
- [C4] N. Q. Hieu, N. H. Chu, D. T. Hoang, D. N. Nguyen, and E. Dutkiewicz, "A unified resource allocation framework for virtual reality streaming over wireless networks," *IEEE International Conference on Communications*, Rome, Italy, May 2023, pp. 3042-3047.
- [C3] N. V. Huynh, N. Q. Hieu, N. H. Chu, D. N. Nguyen, D. T. Hoang, and E. Dutkiewicz, "Defeating eavesdroppers with ambient backscatter communications," *IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking Conference*, Glasgow, United Kingdom, March 2023, pp. 1-6
- [C2] N. Q. Hieu, T. T. Huong, N. T. Hung, N. Q. Thu and N. H. Thanh, "A low-power, high reliable data collection scheme for wireless sensor networks", *International Conference on Advanced Technologies* for Communications (ATC), Hanoi, Vietnam, Oct 2019, pp. 258-263.
- [C1] N. Q. Hieu, N. Huu Thanh, T. T. Huong, N. Quynh Thu and H. V. Quang, "Integrating trickle timing in software defined WSNs for energy efficiency", *IEEE Seventh International Conference on Communications and Electronics (ICCE)*, Hue, Vietnam, Jul 2018, pp. 75-80.

PREPRINTS

- [P3] N. Q. Hieu, D. T. Hoang, D. N. Nguyen, and M. A. Alsheikh, "Reconstructing Human Pose from Inertial Measurements: A Generative Model-based Compressive Sensing Approach," submitted to *IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications* [arXiv].
- [P2] H. Y. Zhu, N. Q. Hieu, D. T. Hoang, D. N. Nguyen, and C.T. Lin, "A Human-Centric Metaverse Enabled by Brain-Computer Interface: A Survey," submitted to *IEEE Communications Surveys & Tutorials* [arXiv].
- [P1] N. Q. Hieu, D. T. Hoang, D. N. Nguyen, V. D. Nguyen, Y. Xiao, and E. Dutkiewicz, "Enhancing Immersion and Presence in the Metaverse with Over-the-Air Brain-Computer Interface", submitted to *IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications* [arXiv].

TEACHING	■ Tutor for IoT Security (42037), UTS	Feb 2023
AWARDS	 Honorary Mention, IEEE ComSoc Student Competition, 	
	"Communications Technology Changing the World"	Nov 2023
	 Outstanding Higher Degree Research Student Award, 	
	School of Electrical and Data Engineering, UTS	Nov 2023
	 IEEE ComSoc Student Travel Grant, IEEE ICC 	Apr 2023
	 ARC DECRA Funded Project Scholarship 	Nov 2021
	 UTS International Research Scholarship (UTS IRS) 	Nov 2021
	 4th place, 35th Student's Scientific Research Contest, HUST 	May 2018
CERTIFICATIONS	■ Research Summer School Certificate - British Council & Newton Fund	Aug 2018
	 Certificate in CCNA Switching and Routing (CISCO) 	Jul 2017

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

- Peer review:
 - IEEE Journals on Selected Areas in Communications (JSAC)
 - IEEE Communications Surveys and Tutorial (COMST)

- IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications (TWC)
- IEEE Transactions on Communications (TCOM)
- IEEE Internet of Things Journal (IOTJ)
- IEEE Transactions on Cognitive Communications and Networking (TCCN)
- IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology (TVT)
- IEEE Wireless Communications Letters (WCL)
- IEEE Communications Letters (CL)
- TPC member:
 - IEEE 97th Vehicular Technology Conference: VTC2023-Spring, 20-23 June 2023, Florence, Italy
 - IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking Conference (WCNC), 26–29 March, 2023, Glasgow, Scotland, UK
 - IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking Conference (WCNC), 10-13 April, 2022, Austin, TX, USA

LANGUAGES

- English: Fluent (speaking, listening, reading, writing).
- Vietnamese: Native.

SKILLS

- Machine Learning: Deep Reinforcement Learning, Deep Learning
- CCNA Switching and Routing
- Programming languages: Python, Java, C/C++
- Simulation tools: Matlab, Cooja, NS2
- Engineering Software/OS: Linux, Contiki OS
- Office tools: Latex, Microsoft Office Tools

REFERENCES

■ Hoang Dinh, Ph.D.

Senior Lecturer

School of Electrical and Data Engineering, Faculty of Information and Technology

University of Technology Sydney

Room 202, Level 8, UTS building 11, Ultimo, NSW 2007, Australia

Email: Hoang.Dinh@uts.edu.au

Diep N. Nguyen, Ph.D.

Associate Professor

School of Electrical and Data Engineering, Faculty of Information and Technology

University of Technology Sydney

Room 303, Level 8, UTS building 11, Ultimo, NSW 2007, Australia

Email: diep.nguyen@uts.edu.au

■ Eryk Dutkiewicz, Ph.D.

Professor

Head of School of Electrical and Data Engineering

Room 102, Level 8, UTS building 11, Ultimo, NSW 2007, Australia

Email: Eryk.Dutkiewicz@uts.edu.au

Dusit Niyato, Ph.D., IEEE Fellow.

Professor

School of Computer Science and Engineering (SCSE) and School of Physical

and Mathematical Sciences (SPMS)

Nanyang Technological University

Block N4-02a-32, Nanyang Avenue, Singapore 639798

Email: dniyato@ntu.edu.sg